Finding Aid for Hickman Price, Jr. Papers 1918-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hickman Price, Jr. Papers 1918-1968
Price, Hickman, 1911-
9 linear feet
Executive with the Kaiser-Frazer Corp., later with Willys Motor Inc. Corporate correspondence, including files concerning his work with Willys-Overland in Brazil; also materials relating to his interest in Latin America, including summary reports prepared for President-elect Kennedy in 1960; miscellaneous correspondence with Adlai Stevenson; and photographs.
85345 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Hickman Price, Jr. (donor no. 4711 ) in 1975.
The collection is open for research.
Hickman Price, Jr. was born on August 14, 1911, in Nashville, Tennessee. He attended Taft School, Philips Exeter Academy, and Columbia University. From 1932 to 1934, he assisted his father as a young man farming wheat in the Texas Panhandle; he then moved on to become a member of the Bankers Trust Company in New York City. After leaving here in 1941, he was appointed chief of the American Economic Mission to the Belgian Congo. Upon returning in 1945, Price was named executive assistant to the president, Graham-Paige Motors Corp. From 1945 to 1952, he was vice president and director of the Kaiser-Frazer Corporation in Willow Run, Michigan. In 1952, Price became president and director of Willys Overland Export Corp., and Willys Overland of Canada, Ltd. In 1954, he was named to be vice president of Willys Motors Inc.
Hickman Price Jr. was a notable figure in the post-war automotive industry. Because of his leadership position with Kaiser-Frazer and Willys Overland, Price helped shape the character of the overseas car market. Widely respected as a businessman, Price was also an influential social and political figure. He was an active Democrat and a staunch supporter of Governor G. Mennen Williams of Michigan and of the presidential aspirations of Adlai Stevenson and John F. Kennedy. Often consulted on matters of relations between the United States and Brazil, Price shared his expertise with members of the Kennedy administration. He further served his country with his appointment as Assistant Secretary of Commerce, a position he held from 1961 to 1963.
The papers of Hickman Price, Jr. document the workings of Willys Overland, Inc. and Kaiser-Frazer Corp, the two corporations which merged in 1953 and which became the principal international producers of the Jeep. Because so much of Price's career was spent in the development of the South American market, the collection includes much information about the role of American businesses in less well-developed economies. The collection is only partially processed.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade--Brazil.; Brazil.; Kaiser-Frazer Corp.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Latin America.; Price, Hickman, 1911-; South America.; Willys-Overland Motors, Inc.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Assembly-line methods.; Automobile industry.; Automobiles.; Brazil.; Industrial buildings.; Interiors.; Laborers.; Price, Hickman, 1911-; Ramos, Joóao Farias.; Willys-Overland Motors, Inc.
Contributors:
Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal Materials
  Personal Materials consists of various family papers, speeches, reports, and financial information. Especially interesting among these materials are several letters addressed to Price from his father, Hickman Price, a prominent agriculturalist.
  - Price Family Papers 1918-1939 (Box 1)
  - Speech entitled, "A Look Ahead in Agriculture" delivered at annual convention of the Farm Equipment Manufacturers 1930 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning agricultural inspection tour of the Soviet Union 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - Memorandum on German Companies prepared for Bankers Trust Co. 1934 (Box 1)
  - Reports prepared for the Bankers Trust Co. 1938, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Income Tax returns 1935-1940 (Box 1)
- Kaiser-Frazer Corporation Files
  The bulk of the collection relates to Price's activities as an executive with the Kaiser-Frazer Corporation. Most of this consists of outgoing correspondence, 1945-1956. Although much of this is fairly typical office correspondence, it does provide some indication of the daily routine of a high-level automobile executive.
  - Board of Director Minutes 1945-1952 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence June 1945-May 1947 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence June 1947-April 1948 (Box 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence August 1948-September 1949 (Box 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence October 1949-May 1951 (Box 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence June 1951-July 1953 (Box 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence April 1954-September 1956 (Box 6)
- Correspondence 1949-1960
  The Correspondence series (1949-1960; 1 linear ft.) consists of letters dealing with business affairs, and social and personal affairs of Hickman Price, Jr. Included here is Price's correspondence as Assistant Secretary of Commerce, family correspondence, and social communications with business and political figures. The bulk of the correspondence relates to the business of Willys Overland and Kaiser-Frazer. This includes correspondence with suppliers and distributors, personnel, foreign branch offices, and domestic divisions within the corporation. A sizeable amount of the correspondence is in Portuguese, but the bulk is in English.
  - Accident 1957 (Box 7)
  - Assistant Secretary of Commerce 1961-1963 (Box 7)
  - Biography: John Ewing Price 1945-1946 (Box 7)
    (Includes information about Price's biography of his grandfather as submitted to The National Cyclopedia of American Biography)
  - Family Correspondence
    - 1945-1951 (Box 7)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 7)
    - 1956 (Box 7)
    - 1957 (Box 7)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - 1960 (Box 7)
  - Ingoing and outgoing correspondence
    - 1944-1945 (Box 7)
    - 1946 (Box 7)
    - 1947 (Box 7)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 7)
    - 1950 (Box 7)
    - 1951 (Box 7)
    - 1952, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (includes correspondence with Adlai Stevenson)
    - 1953, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1954 (Box 7)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - 1957, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - 1960 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1963 (Box 7)
    - 1968 (Box 7)
  - Merger 1953 (Box 7)
    (Correspondence relating to the merger of Kaiser-Frazer and Willys Overland)
  - Product Demonstrations 1951 (Box 7)
  - Undated (Box 7)
    (Contains administrative and legal documents concerning the expansion of Willys Overland of Brazil; and procedures for obtaining the Douglas Long Beach Plant)
  - Williams, G. Mennen 1955-1959 (Box 7)
- Administrative 1947-1956
  The Administrative series (1947-1956; .5 linear ft.) consists of records and minutes of various departmental divisions within Willys Overland and Kaiser-Frazer; official reports and policies and goals of the corporation; lists of cable codes designed to insure privacy in cabled messages; mailing lists; legal documents; and some organizational charts. The reports are especially interesting in that they portray the extent to which Willys Overland was involved in international economic and political affairs. Most of these reports were written by Price, and his predecessor Marcel DeMuller.
  - Cable Codes, Willys Overland 1952 (Box 8)
  - Export Policy and Service, Willys Overland 1946-1952 (Box 8)
  - Fleet Sales Program, Willys Overland 1949-1953 (Box 8)
  - Legal Documents and Agreements 1949-1959 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, Willys Overland 1947-1952 (Box 8)
  - Organizational Charts undated (Box 8)
  - Proposed Farm Equipment, Willys Overland 1948 (Box 8)
  - Reports 1947-1963
    - DeMuller, 1 folders
      - "Export Sales Outlook," 1948 (Box 8)
      - Speech on the Geneva Conference, New York Times Export Issue 1947 (Box 8)
      - "World Report," 1947 (Box 8)
    - Price, 1 folders
      - "Address At The Opening of the U.S.A. Exhibit in Rio," 1963 (Box 8)
      - "American Week Speech, Brazilian Business," 1959 (Box 8)
      - "An American Industrialist Speaks To Us" (Box 8)
      - "Background Notes and Suggestions of Policy on Latin America," 1960 (Box 8)
      - "Holland, Germany, and Switzerland," 1948 (Box 8)
      - "President-Elect Janio Quadros of Brazil," 1960 (Box 8)
      - "Report on Middle East," 1947 (Box 8)
      - "Report on India," 1947 (Box 8)
      - "Survey of the Far East," 1947 (Box 8)
      - re United States cooperation on Brazilian economic life 1959 (Box 8)
- Financial 1945-1967
  The Financial series (1945-1967; .5 linear ft.) is divided into two subseries: corporate and personal. The corporate subseries documents some of the financial affairs of Willys Overland and Kaiser-Frazer. Included are account books, budgetary information, and financial statements. This subseries is valuable for its financial overview of the two companies in the period from 1945 to 1952. To be found in these files are annual expenditures, product prices, and other figures that reflect typical transactions. The second subseries included here deals with personal finances and consists of personal receipts, tax information, and stocks and securities of Price and his family.
  - Corporate
    - Kaiser-Frazer
      - Account Books, 3 volumes (Box 8)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 8)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 8)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 8)
      - General Financial Statements 1949-1951 (Box 8)
    - Willys Overland
      - Brazil Plant and Production Expenses 1954, 1 volumes (Box 8)
      - Cost Reduction Check List (Box 8)
      - Expense Vouchers 1950-1954, 1 volumes (Box 8)
      - Financial Statements, 4 volumes
        - September 1952 (Box 8)
        - October 1952 (Box 8)
        - November 1952 (Box 8)
        - February 1953 (Box 8)
      - General Financial Information (Box 8)
      - Price Bulletins 1952 (Box 8)
      - Revised Budget 1952, 1 volumes (Box 8)
      - Supplier Agreements 1952, 1 volumes (Box 8)
  - Personal
    - General Family Finances 1946-1959 (Box 8)
    - Income Tax, U.S. and Brazil
      - 1955 (Box 8)
      - 1956 (Box 8)
      - 1957 (Box 8)
      - 1958 (Box 8)
      - 1959 (Box 8)
      - 1960 (Box 8)
- Published and Printed Information 1947-1959
  Printed And Published Information (1947-1959; .5 linear ft.) consists in part of advertisements for the products of the Willys Overland and Kaiser-Frazer companies. This series documents the public face of a car company and the strategy it used to sell its product. Other materials in this series include magazines, pamphlets, product description brochures, and other materials published by Willys Overland advertising their products and outlining their ongoing activities.
  - Newspapers
    (Contains a number of newspaper clippings, mostly from Brazilian papers, in Portuguese)
    - 1946 (Box 9)
    - 1951 (Box 9)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 9)
    - 1957 (Box 9)
    - 1958, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1959 (Box 9)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 9)
  - Product Materials 1947-1950
    - Export Sedan, 4-63 1947 (Box 9)
    - Model MC 38 Military Jeep 1950 (Box 9)
    - Technical Specifications, Jeep Commercial and Truck Chassis 1947 (Box 9)
  - Published materials circa 1950-1960, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks 1950-1960
    - Scrapbook 1952, 1 volumes (Box 9)
      (newspaper clippings in Portuguese)
    - Scrapbook 1957, 1 volumes (Box 9)
      (newspaper clippings from the Sao Paulo paper in Brazil, in Portuguese)
    - Dauphine Project Report 1959, 1 volumes (Box 9)
      (in Portuguese)
    - Assistant Secretary of Commerce Scrapbook (Box 9)
      (includes congratulatory and laudatory letters addressed to Mr. Price at the conclusion of his post)
- Photographs, 1950-1960
  The last series, Photographs (1950-1960; .5 linear ft.) consists of photographs of Hickman Price, Jr. and his business associates in many different countries, but especially in South America. Also to be found here are photos of Marcel DeMuller, the previous president of Willys Overland. Many vehicles produced by Willys Overland and Kaiser-Frazer are also documented here. The photographs are divided into six topical categories: DeMuller, Marcel; Family photos and portraits; Hickman Price, Jr. and Business Associates; Margaret Bayne Price; Production and Manufacture; and Vehicles.
  - DeMuller (Box 9)
    (Previous president and general manager of Willys Overland, killed in 1952)
  - Family photos and portraits (Box 9)
    (Includes photos of Price, Mrs. Price, and their two sons)
  - Hickman Price, Jr. and Business Associates (Box 9)
    (Various pictures of Price with other businessmen, in both large and small groups, mostly South American)
  - Price, Margaret Bayne (Box 9)
    (Photos of Mrs. Price receiving an award at South American ceremony; newspaper article attached, in Portuguese)
  - Production and Manufacture (Box 9)
    (Documents various stages of the production and manufacture of the Willys Overland vehicles)
  - Vehicles
    - Jeeps (Box 9)
    - Jeep Truck (Box 9)
    - Triumph Sportscar (Box 9)